This nested loop configuration,
在这个循环嵌套结构里
this smaller loop inside,
里面的这个小循环
is usually referred to as the inner loop.
通常被称为内循环
Every time this outer loop steps inside,
每当外循环进入这里面
it would restart this inner loop's counter to zero again,
它就会将循环计数器重设为 0
forcing it to print this, "Hi!"
迫使其输出 “Hi” 这条信息三次
message three times, which means this outer loop would cause
也就是说 外循环将会
this message to be repeated three times again and again, three consecutive times.
重复执行输出 3 遍信息 每次连续输出三次
That's why this message would be printed out nine times in total.
这就是这条信息总共会输出九次的原因
But let's trace this program step-by-step and
我们现在来跟踪这个程序的每一步
watch our variables i and j change as we go.
看看变量 i 和 j 是怎么变化的
Starting with the outer loop,
开始外循环
i is initialized to zero,
i 初始化为 0
setting its value to zero and then
将其值设为 0
the next thing that happens is we check if i is less than three.
然后判断 i 是否小于 3
In this case it is,
是的
so it steps inside and goes into this inner loop.
于是进到这里面 来到内循环
What happens now is that j gets initialized to zero, getting that value,
因此 j 被初始化为 0 记下这个值
and then we check if j is less than three,
然后判断 j 是否小于 3
which it is, so we step inside the inner loop,
是的 于是进入内循环
printing out the statement, "Hi!".
输出语句 “Hi!”
And then we reach the end of the inner loop, so we go back up,
到达内循环尾部 我们回到这上面来
and check and increment j by one,
判断 给 j 加 1
changing its value from zero to one.
使其值从 0 变为 1
And then once we increment it,
增量好后
we check that j is still less than three,
判断 j 是否仍小于 3
which in this case it is,
是的
so we step inside the loop again and we print out another, "Hi!"
所以再次进入循环 再次输出 “Hi!”
or reach the end of the inner loop,
到达循环尾部
so we go back up and add one more to j.
于是我们回到这上面来 再给 j 加 1
Then we check if j is still less than three which it is,
判断 j 是否仍小于 3 是的
so we step inside the loop again and we print out "Hi!", one more time.
所以再次进入循环 又一次输出 “Hi!”
This time we reached the end of the loop,
现在我们到了循环尾部
we go back up and increment by one,
回来 给 j 加 1
making it three, so when we check that j is less than three this time,
使其为 3 再次判断 j 是否小于 3
it's no longer true.
条件不再为真
So that just jumps all the way to the end of this inner loop and continues from there.
所以直接跳到内循环末尾 从这里继续往下
And since there's nothing after this inner loop,
不过内循环之后就没有东西了
so we reach this closing bracket of the outer loop,
所以我们到了外循环的右括号这
which means we go back up and we increment i this time,
也就意味着我们得回去 这次得给 i 增量
i changes from zero to one.
i 从 0 变为 1
So, we check if i is still less than three,which it is in that case,
判断 i 是否仍小于 3 是的
and that means we step into that loop.
意味着我们要进入循环
Now that we've stepped into this outer loop,
进入外循环
we see this inner loop all over again,
我们又看到了这个内循环
so we start from the beginning including the initialization step and j goes back to zero.
所以我们得从头开始 包括执行初始化操作 于是 j 重置为 0
So we check if j is less than three,
然后判断 j 是否小于 3
which it is and then we start printing again,
是的 所以再次输出
so "Hi!" gets printed out.
于是 Hi! 得以再次被输出
And then we reach the closing bracket of the inner loop,
到达内循环右括号
so we go back up and increment j,
回来 给 j 增量
going from zero to one and then checking if it's less than three,
从 0 变为 1 判断是否小于 3
which it is, so we print out "Hi!"
是的 于是再次输出 “Hi!”
again and then we end the inner loop again,
再次结束内循环
go back up, increment it to two,
回来 将其增量为 2
check if it's less than three,
判断是否小于 3
which it is, so we print out"Hi!"
是的
again. And then we repeat this until we get j++ to make our value three,
又一次输出 “Hi!” 重复这一步 直到 j++ 把值变为 3
so when we check if j is less than three,
这个时候我们判断 j 是否小于 3
which it's not in the case,
条件就不再为真了
we don't print anything and we skip to the closing bracket of the inner loop.
我们不再输出任何东西 跳到内循环的右括号来
And then, we move on we don't have anything else to do,
继续 后面没有别的操作了
so we reach the closing bracket of the outer loop but i is still less than three,
于是到达外循环的右括号 而 i 仍小于 3
so we go back up,
所以回来
we increment i to make it two and we check if i is less than three or not,
将 i 增量为 2 判断 i 是否小于 3
which in this case it is,
是的
so we step into the inner loop again,
所以再次进入内循环
initializing j again making it zero.
再次将 j 初始化为 0
And then because zero is less than three,
由于 0 小于 3
so we start printing all over again.
所以我们又要开始输出了
And this would force our inner loop to go over and
这会使得内循环不断重复
over its normal cycle and print out "Hi! "
输出 “Hi!”
three times again.
还是连续三次
Now after the inner loop reaches the value of three,
等到内循环计数器变为 3 后
this condition becomes false and we skip to the end and then we reach
这个条件变为假 所以我们直接跳到尾部
the closing bracket of the outer loop and we go back
到达外循环的右括号 再回来
up and increment i making it three this time,
这次将 i 增量为 3
which is no longer less than three,
而 3 不再小于 3
so it doesn't even step into this inner loop anymore.
因此不会再进入内循环了
And it just simply jumps to the closing bracket of the outer loop and the program ends.
而是直接跳到外循环的右括号 程序结束
Now if you've noticed, i changed from zero to three and every time i had a value,
不知道你是否有注意 i 会从 0 变为 3 而 i 每增加一个值
j changed from zero to three.
j 就会从 0 变为 3
This is the idea of nested loops,
这就是循环嵌套的原理
where you could use i and j interchangeably inside the inner loop, in many occasions.
很多情况下 你可以在内循环中交替使用 i 和 j
Let's see how we could use nested loops to
打个比方 我们来看看如何用循环嵌套
navigate through a two-dimensional array, for example.
来访问一个二维数组
Going back to our two-dimensional grid here,
回到这里的二维网格
we want to see how we can go through every single number in this two-dimensional array.
我们想知道如何访问这个二维数组里的每个数字
We already know that if we wanted to go through every item in a single row,
我们已经知道 如果想访问一行里的每一项
we can simply write a loop for that.
我们只需写一个循环就行了
This loop, for example,
而这个循环
would go through every single item in row with index zero,
会访问索引为 0 的行的每一项
which means it would count all these numbers and because it's adding them to total,
也就意味着它会统计这些数字 因为我们是把它们和 total 相加
now by the end of this loop,
所以等循环结束后
we'd have the value of total equal to the sum of the items in that row.
我们 total 的值就会等于该行中所有项的总和
If we wanted to add all the other rows,
如果我们想把其它行也加进来
we could simply write a loop for each row.
那我们可以为每一行写一个循环
The only difference is the index here,
唯一不同的是这里的索引
matching the index of the row that we're interested in.
要换成目的行的索引
So once we run this code,
等我们运行这些代码
it would go through every single row and then
程序就会访问每一行
every single item in that row and add them up until we get the total value we want.
以及行里的每一项 然后不断地累加 直到我们得到了想要的 total 值
However if you noticed, all these loops are almost identical except for that index,
不过如果你有注意到的话 你会发现这些循环除了索引 几乎一模一样
which happens to change from zero to three.
而索引是从 0 变为 3 的
That looks like something we could use a loop for.
看起来我们好像可以把这些套到循环里
If we surround one of those loops with
如果我们把其中一个循环
another loop and use its loop counter instead of this index,
用另一个循环套起来 然后用这一整个循环的计数器作为索引
it would do the exact same thing that this code is doing.
那么这个大循环会和这些代码具备一样的功能
So if we replace this code with something that looks like this,
所以 如果我们把这些代码换成这样
where we have this nested loop configuration here,
也就是在这使用循环嵌套结构
one that uses the loop counter i and the other that uses the loop counter j.
一个循环用循环计数器 i 另一个用计数器 j
And if we try to access grades of i and j,
如果我们访问 grades [i] [j]
this would eventually add all the items in the two-dimensional array.
程序最终就会把数组里的所有项都累加起来
So running this code,
执行这段代码
the inner loop would go through every single item in
内循环就会访问一行里的每一项
a row and then the outer loop would make sure that we
而外循环则确保我们会移到下一行
switch to the next row and then the inner loop would
接着内循环再访问这一行里的每一项
go through every item in it again and that way,
这么一来
we can guarantee that by the end of the code,
我们就能确保 等代码执行完毕后
we've seen every single item in the grid.
我们已经将网格里的每一项都访问完毕了
And because every time we are adding the grades into our variable total,
由于每次我们都把 grades 的值与变量 total 相加
by the end of this nested loop configuration,
所以等这个循环嵌套结束后
total would have the sum of every single number in this two-dimensional array.
total 就会是这个二维数组里所有值的总和
Perfect. You can do a lot more than just add the numbers.
完美 除了累加 你能做的还有很多
You could, for example, try to find the minimum number and
比如 你可以找出二维数组里的最小值和最大值
the maximum number in a two-dimensional array using this nested loop configuration.
方法也是用这个循环嵌套结构